Since 2003, a special type of scam targeting the elderly
Seit 2003 zielt eine Betrugsmasche auf alte Leute
called the money transfer scam has proliferated in Japan.
in Japan ab, der Überweisungsbetrug.
Financial damages increased every year, reaching 56.5 billion yen in 2014.
Der finanzielle Schaden stieg jährlich und belief sich 2014 auf 56,5 Milliarden Yen.
Now, in 2019, scammers have changed their techniques,
2019 haben die Betrüger ihre Masche geändert,
and the damage continues.
und der Betrug geht weiter.
CHIBA PREFECTURAL POLICE
PRÄFEKTURTPOLIZEI CHIBA
Stop!
Halt!
Let go of me!
Lasst mich los!
You're alive.
Du lebst.
I don't die easily.
Ich sterbe nicht so leicht.
EPISODE 9
FOLGE 9
I need a little help.
Ich brauche Hilfe.
How much money you got?
Wie viel Geld hast du?
Money? I don't have any. I used it all.
Geld? Keins. Alles aufgebraucht.
Liar.
Lügner.
You're holding cash, right?
Du hast Bargeld, oder?
I failed as a conman.
Ich habe als Betrüger versagt.
Serves you right!
Geschieht dir recht!
Seriously.
Im Ernst.
-I've run out of options. -It's the same for me--
-Mir gehen die Möglichkeiten aus. -Mir auch...
Hand over all of the cash you've got!
Gib mir dein ganzes Bargeld!
If you don't, I'll go get it from your house!
Wenn nicht, hole ich es bei dir zu Hause!
Go ahead.
Mach nur.
A piece of trash like you can't do anything on your own, anyway!
Ein Scheißkerl wie du kann eh nichts selbst!
What did you say?
Was hast du gesagt?
Wait!
Warte!
I'll kill you!
Ich töte dich!
Makoto!
Makoto!
Some of your friends broke into the house!
Ein paar deiner Freund sind eingebrochen!
I know. I saw Misaki.
Ich weiß. Ich habe Misaki gesehen.
-Misaki-chan... -What about the cops?
-Misaki-chan... -Und die Polizei?
I didn't tell them anything.
Ich habe nichts verraten.
That's good. For now, just act normal.
Gut. Verhalt dich momentan normal.
Normal?
Normal?
Yamada?
Yamada?
No, it's me! Get over to the office.
Nein, ich bin's! Komm ins Büro.
Dokugawa-san? But, I...
Dokugawa-san? Aber ich...
Kanbe-san has talked to Tojo.
Kanbe-san hat mit Tojo geredet.
Get your ass over here! Or else...
Schwing deinen Arsch hierher! Sonst...
What is it?
Was ist los?
-I have to go. -Where?
-Ich muss weg. -Wohin?
I'll be right back!
Bin gleich zurück!
Makoto! I got a call from the hospital!
Makoto! Das Krankenhaus hat angerufen!
Your dad's coming home today...
Dein Vater kommt heute heim...
Hey, get to work!
Los, an die Arbeit!
Damn...
Verdammt...
Cover these in paint.
Mal die an.
Hurry up!
Schnell!
Use the pole to mix it in.
Misch sie mit dem Stecken.
Like this, you idiot!
So, du Idiot!
Thank you very much.
Vielen Dank.
We did it!
Wir haben es geschafft!
Yes.
Ja.
We'll draw straws for how many pages.
Wir ziehen Strohhalme um die Anzahl der Seiten.
Why don't they try to share it with all of you who are suffering?
Warum teilen sie es nicht mit euch, die ihr leidet?
That's why the elderly are a cancer on Japan.
Darum sind die Alten der Krebs Japans.
If you hang on to this job, you'll never have to feel insecure
Wenn ihr dabei bleibt, müsst ihr euch nie mehr unsicher
or unfulfilled or frustrated ever again.
oder unausgelastet oder frustriert fühlen.
You five have been chosen.
Ihr fünf wurdet ausgewählt.
THE ELDERLY ARE A CANCER ON JAPAN
DIE ALTEN SIND JAPANS KREBS
Down with the elderly disease!
Nieder mit der Alten-Krankheit!
-Down with the elderly disease! -Good!
-Nieder mit der Alten-Krankheit! -Gut!
-Call the head office. -Yes, sir.
-Ruf das Hauptbüro an. -Ja.
Listen up.
Hört zu.
Even if you're caught, keep your mouths shut.
Wenn ihr erwischt werdet, schweigt.
-Yes.
-Ja.
Good.
Gut.
And now your work is finished. Get out of here!
Eure Arbeit ist beendet. Verschwindet!
Dokugawa-san.
Dokugawa-san.
Misaki...
Misaki...
I'm sorry.
Tut mir leid.
What did the cops say?
Was hat die Polizei gesagt?
Leave.
Geh.
-Please, don't say anything to-- -Leave!
-Bitte, sag nichts zur... -Geh!
What are you doing?
Was machst du?
I told you, your dad gets home today.
Dein Vater kommt doch heute heim.
I'm making a cake to celebrate.
Zur Feier backe ich einen Kuchen.
A cake?
Einen Kuchen?
This isn't the time for that.
Das ist nicht angebracht.
You told me, didn't you? I need to act normal.
Du hast doch gesagt, ich soll mich normal benehmen.
Okay. I'll help.
Ok. Ich helfe dir.
Let's start over again, as a family.
Fangen wir als Familie neu an.
From the beginning.
Von vorne.
-Okay? -Okay.
-Ok? -Ok.
Okay.
Ok.
Let me.
Lass mich mal.
It's just like old times!
Wie in alten Zeiten!
When you were little, you always made the frosting.
Als du klein warst, hast du die Glasur gemacht.
Do you remember?
Erinnerst du dich?
Yeah, I remember.
Ja, ich erinnere mich.
Wait, no.
Warte, nein.
What was it?
Was war das?
That half-baked dough inside the pancakes you made.
Der halbrohe Teig in deinen Pfannkuchen.
That was my favorite.
Den mochte ich am liebsten.
That's right.
Stimmt.
I was always telling you you'd get sick if you ate too much.
Ich sagte immer, dir wird schlecht, wenn du zu viel davon isst.
Me and Misaki.
Ich und Misaki.
She's been chiding me ever since we were kids.
Sie schimpft mich, seit wir Kinder waren.
Misaki-chan...
Misaki-chan...
I'm so sorry.
Es tut mir so leid.
She was so scared.
Sie hatte solche Angst.
Hey!
Hey!
You! Makoto!
Du! Makoto!
Stop ignoring me!
Hör auf, mich zu ignorieren!
Hey!
Hey!
Makoto!
Makoto!
Does he ever shut up?
Hält er mal die Klappe?
This is all I have.
Mehr habe ich nicht.
-This is it? -That's what I'm telling you!
-Das ist alles? -Sag ich doch!
You're not hiding any, are you?
Du versteckst nichts, oder?
I told you this is all I have!
Ich sagte doch, mehr habe ich nicht!
You're really pissing me off.
Du machst mich echt sauer.
I'm busy, so get out of here!
Ich bin beschäftigt, also verschwinde!
-What'd you say? -I said get out of here, asshole!
-Was hast du gesagt? -Ich sagte, verschwinde, Arschloch!
-I'll kill your mom! -Shut up!
-Ich töte deine Mutter! -Schnauze!
-She said the baby was just born. -Is that so?
-Sie sagte, das Baby wurde erst geboren. -Aha?
I've caused a lot of trouble for you.
Ich habe dir viel Ärger bereitet.
It happens all the time.
Passiert ständig.
We'll take a little break and then get back into it.
Wir machen kurz Pause und stürzen uns dann wieder rein.
About that...
Deswegen...
-How do you feel about being the leader? -What?
-Wie gefällt es dir als Anführer? -Was?
Thank you so much!
Vielen Dank!
Thank you.
Danke.
Thank you very much, young man.
Vielen Dank, junger Mann.
Take care.
Machen Sie's gut.
You know, I'm tired.
Ich bin müde.
All of the stores and people,
Die Läden und Leute
I'm giving them to you.
übergebe ich dir.
Of course, I'll take care of everything with Tojo.
Natürlich kümmere ich mich um alles, was Tojo angeht.
What do you think?
Was meinst du?
You're joking, right? Kanbe-san.
Das ist ein Witz, oder? Kanbe-san.
No.
Nein.
I'm serious.
Ich meine es ernst.
But what will you do once you quit?
Aber was machst du, wenn du aufgehört hast?
Move over to the financing side?
Wechselst du zu den Finanziers?
I don't think so.
Eher nicht.
I haven't really thought about it yet, but...
Ich habe noch nicht drüber nachgedacht, aber...
I think I'll try my hand at a normal job.
...ich versuche es wohl mit einem normalen Job.
I wonder if...
Ich frage mich, ob...
it's possible to change after all this time.
...es möglich ist, sich nach all der Zeit zu ändern.
I'll try.
Ich versuche es.
Wait, what's wrong?
Halt, was ist los?
-Isn't it this? -Is it?
-Ist es nicht der? -Ja?
Okay.
Ok.
Are you okay?
Alles ok?
-Did you hurt yourself? -I'm fine, sorry.
-Hast du dir wehgetan? -Alles gut, tut mir leid.
-I'll get a towel. -Thanks.
-Ich hole ein Tuch. -Danke.
Let's see.
Mal sehen.
-Here. -Thank you.
-Hier. -Danke.
I'm sorry.
Tut mir leid.
I'm going to quit.
Ich werde aufhören.
I didn't know what to do.
Ich wusste nicht, was ich tun soll.
Dad got sick,
Papa wurde krank,
and we had no money,
wir hatten kein Geld,
and I couldn't find a job.
und ich fand keinen Job.
The social welfare services did nothing to help us.
Die Wohlfahrt tat nichts, um uns zu helfen.
But I knew I needed to do something.
Aber ich wusste, dass ich was tun musste.
I didn't want to do anything bad.
Ich wollte nichts Böses tun.
I just...
Ich...
I didn't have a choice.
Ich hatte keine Wahl.
I'm so sorry.
Tut mir so leid.
Makoto...
Makoto...
I don't think that's right.
Das ist nicht richtig.
It's your dad!
Das ist dein Vater!
Hello!
Hallo!
Welcome--
Willkommen...
Is your son here?
Ist Ihr Sohn da?
-Find him. -Yes, sir!
-Such ihn. -Jawohl!
-You check over there. -Got it.
-Schau da drüben nach. -Verstanden.
I found him!
Ich habe ihn gefunden!
-Stop! -Hey!
-Halt! -Hey!
Stop!
Halt!
-Come with us! -No!
-Kommen Sie mit! -Nein!
Makoto Kusano.
Makoto Kusano.
You're under arrest.
Sie sind verhaftet.
Let go of me!
Loslassen!
Stop!
Aufhören!
Get up!
Aufstehen!
Let go of me!
Loslassen!
You didn't only take money from your victims...
Sie haben den Opfern nicht nur Geld genommen...
you took their dignity!
...sondern auch ihre Würde!
Shut up!
Klappe!
You destroyed their dignity.
Sie haben ihre Würde zerstört.
-Let go of me! -Do you know
-Loslassen! -Wissen Sie,
-how much they suffered? -Let go!
-wie sehr sie gelitten haben? -Loslassen!
-Stop! -Depression.
-Aufhören! -Depressionen.
Suicide.
Suizid.
Did you think about that?
Mal daran gedacht?
-Shut up! -Your crime isn't scamming.
-Klappe! -Sie haben nicht betrogen.
-Keep moving!
-Bewegung!
It's murder!
Sondern gemordet!
-Let me go! -Makoto!
-Loslassen! -Makoto!
-Mom! -Get up!
-Mama! -Aufstehen!
Makoto!
Makoto!
Stop fighting!
Wehren Sie sich nicht!
-Mom! -Makoto!
-Mama! -Makoto!
Come on!
Na los!
I...
Ich...
I did the best I could!
Ich habe mein Bestes getan!
I did everything I could!
Ich gab alles!
-Get up! -No one...
-Aufstehen! -Niemand...
Get up!
Aufstehen!
No one was going to help us!
Niemand wollte uns helfen!
Don't let him go!
Nicht loslassen!
What was I supposed to do?
Was sollte ich tun?
Hold on to him!
Haltet ihn fest!
Stop!
Aufhören!
-Kusano! -Stop!
-Kusano! -Halt!
Let go of me!
Loslassen!
-Makoto! -Let go!
-Makoto! -Loslassen!
-Quickly! -Makoto!
-Schnell! -Makoto!
-Get in! -No!
-Rein da! -Nein!
Makoto! Makoto!
Makoto!
Let me go!
Loslassen!
We won't just help you around the house.
Wir helfen Ihnen nicht nur zu Hause.
If you join our A plan,
Mit unserem A-Plan,
in addition to daily safety checks,
zusätzlich zu den täglichen Sicherheitsprüfungen,
we'll also provide support when you're hospitalized or move to a care facility,
bieten wir Ihnen Unterstützung im Krankenhaus oder Pflegeheim,
as well as for funeral and cremation services.
ebenso bei Begräbnis und Verbrennung.
Okay.
Ok.
Things sure are convenient nowadays.
Heutzutage ist es praktischer.
I don't have any family to care for me,
Ich habe keine Familie, die sich kümmert,
so this would be a big help.
das wäre eine große Hilfe.
Thank you.
Danke.
It was a long time ago,
Das ist lange her,
but my son used to be a good swimmer.
aber mein Sohn war ein guter Schwimmer.
Maybe some time, he could bring his friends from the team
Er könnte mal mit seinen Freunden aus dem Team
over to the house.
bei Ihnen vorbeikommen.
Yes, of course!
Ja, sicher!
Our mission is to remove the anxiety
Unsere Mission ist es, die Ängste zu nehmen,
that comes from living alone so that you can enjoy your golden years.
die das Leben alleine bringt, damit Sie Ihren Lebensabend genießen.
We're currently offering a discount that brings the total price down
Wir bieten gerade einen Rabatt, so sinkt der Gesamtpreis
from two million yen to only 1.8 million yen.
von zwei Millionen Yen auf 1,8 Millionen Yen.
Really?
Wirklich?
It's a great discount.
Ein toller Rabatt.
Thank you very much.
Vielen Dank.
Thank you.
Danke.
It's legal, I get to make old men and women happy,
Es ist legal, ich mache alte Leute glücklich,
and I'm making money.
und ich verdiene Geld.
What a great job.
Ein toller Job.
No replies.
Keine Antwort.
Kusano...
Kusano...
what are you doing?
...was machst du?
HEADQUARTERS FOR SPECIAL FRAUD
HAUPTSITZ FÜR SONDERBETRUG
CURRENTLY HIRING POLICE OFFICERS
WIR STELLEN EIN: POLIZISTEN
Kusano, get up.
Kusano, stehen Sie auf.
If Misaki Azuma hadn't rescinded her testimony...
Hätte Misaki Azuma ihre Aussage nicht zurückgezogen...
I could have thrown you in prison.
...hätte ich Sie ins Gefängnis geworfen.
Be ready.
Seien Sie wachsam.
I won't let you get away next time.
Nächstes Mal kommen Sie nicht davon.
The world is cruel?
Die Welt ist grausam?
No one will save us?
Niemand rettet uns?
I won't accept that!
Das akzeptiere ich nicht!
Hey, Makoto.
Hey, Makoto.
Long time no see.
Lange nicht gesehen.
Subtitle translation by Marti McElreath
Untertitel von: Sonja Schmidt